hey everyone welcome back to this tosa
playlist and we are talking about API
testing now we have seen many different
features of API uh how you can scan Uris
how you can create your test cases how
you can uh put verifications in your
test cases and then when we talking
about API scan you can scan both file as
well as a URI you can um also um run and
check your apis are working correctly or
not right so you have seen all of this
but let's see some more options uh which
are available with this particular tool
which is API scan okay so we are going
to uh talk about this message section
okay so there are different options like
search and payload uh validate uh the
split print and WRA right so what all of
these options mean and how they can help
you uh validate or check your API
whether they are um as expected or they
are working as expected
right so for this uh let's go ahead and
uh scan a particular URI so that we can
get some messages um I'm going to use
our pet store Swagger um
IO okay um so once we scan this it will
create this folder structure with all
the messages we have already seen in
this right now if I go into a particular
message like this post message okay um
and this is going to add some
information right so it's a post method
and it has got an endpoint a resource
right now um if you are scanning a
particular API right um maybe it's uh
newly developed and you don't know
whether it is correctly structured or
maybe it is scanned correctly by tosa
API scan itself right so API scan has a
feature called validate which can
validate uh this whole message or the
structure and also uh the elements right
if anything is missing in this
particular uh Json format okay so uh
what you can do you can go to your
message and then you just need to click
on validate okay and once you click on
that it will show you a message that no
error found uh on the bottom okay now if
I go ahead and remove this curly brace
okay so this is a
invalid uh invalid Json structure right
and now if I go to validate and I click
on validate you will see there are
validation errors okay so it is saying
uh Json token and array is not valid for
closing Json type object okay and it
will also tell you the line and the
position so using this feature you can
can basically find out whether your API
message is correct um or uh it is as per
the required specifications before uh
you go ahead and test this API okay or
even if you send the message you are not
going to get a response back okay so if
you face uh some issues in your message
you can go ahead and validate that and
that will show you the errors which are
there and uh then you can go ahead and
correct that error right now after I
correct this error and click on validate
it will show me no error found okay so
it's a quite uh useful feature if you
want to check whether your messages are
correct or not
okay the next option uh this pretty
print right so what it does uh it
basically uh puts your structure back
into a specific format right so if it is
adjacent so it will basically uh make it
a printable like format okay so if I now
do this right so if I I have written
this complete message and you can see
this structure is not looking so nice
right so what I can do here I can come
to a message and I can click on this
pretty print and you will see it will
now restructure my message uh into the
required format okay so with the
required spaces and U the
required required lines right so it has
structured basically based on whatever
message format it is okay so this pretty
print is for that it adjust the line
brakes and ident indentation of the
payload message
okay now coming to the next option which
is word wrap it basically does uh like
the name suggest it wraps um a really
long line uh with lots of different
words into uh different lines right so
let's see an example for this
uh let me create a new message here okay
and in this new message I'm going to
paste something okay so I have this Json
file uh which has been uh which is for
the pet store okay it is a Json source
file and uh if I open this you will see
that uh it has got lots of uh Json
Source right so if I copy this whole
text okay if I copy this this here and I
come here and I paste it here you will
see that it is really a long line right
so everything is written in just one
line or maybe two lines right but it's
really long and it's very difficult to
even read anything here
right so uh for this this kind of uh
situations this word RP is present okay
so you can come to this message and uh
you can click on word WP and you will
see that now everything is contained
inside this particular uh page right so
and based on that it has now uh
restructured it and it has made multiple
lens instead of just two lens okay now
if you want to make it more better then
click on pred print and now you will get
the whole file in the Json structure
right so these two are really useful uh
when you are trying to find out
something in your Json source files or
any other source files right you can use
the wordp and then you can do a pretty
print and then you will see that it is
in the required format now it is very
easy to uh whatever I want to find I can
come here and find anything
right so um yeah that's that's very
useful feature called word RP and we
have seen print the last option uh which
is present is this search in payload
okay so if I go back to my post
message and I can search any particular
text in this particular uh payload
message okay so if I want to search for
ID then um I can do a find next and it
will highlight that so this way you can
find any particular text in your payload
message if your message is quite long
and if you find want to find some text
in that particular message you can use
this feature right you can also mix it
with a different uh filters like match
case match whole word you can use leg
expression wild cards uh you can also do
a search up which will basically search
uh the text in the upward Direction okay
instead of downward
Direction um also there is a replace
option so if I want to replace some uh
any text with uh some other text I can
do that right so for example this range
uh text is here for the name okay and if
I want to change it to range one I can
do a replace and that is going to
replace that particular text or I can
also do a replace all and it will
replace everything right I probably did
some mistake here or something was
changed okay but I can do it again so I
can change it to range and I can do a
replace okay so it has uh changed to
range one and then it will also tell you
that there are no more text with this
particular name range no more
occurrences found right so this way uh
you can do a pretty easy uh find and
replace uh in your payload messages
using this particular feature okay so
all of these four options search in
payload validate Prett print word RP
help you uh do a lot of things uh in
your API messages okay basically
validate them or maybe restructure them
or maybe change few things right so
these are all helpful when you are
looking at some new API messages which
has been developed recently and uh
before you start testing them or before
you start checking them you can perform
all of these different operations using
this options um available in API
scan so that's all for this video uh
hopefully you enjoyed it and you learned
something new today uh do tuning to our
Channel as we'll be speaking more about
some of the other features which are
available with API scan we'll also talk
about how you can scan a soap API
request right until now we have been
looking at the rest API request so do
tune to our channel to check out for all
these new videos or do subscribe to our
Channel if youve not already done it and
we'll look at an interesting topic in
the next video Until then uh keep
learning tosa uh in our Channel and do
let us know if you have any other
suggestions
to learn any new topic related to tosa
or any other automation tool